<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article class="specification">

  <articleinfo>
    <title>MMBase Poll</title>
    <date>2006-12-08</date>
    <edition>$Id$</edition>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Michiel</firstname>
        <surname>Meeuwissen</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <abstract>
      <para>Poll</para>
    </abstract>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>
      <para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site. See <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink></para>
    </legalnotice>

  </articleinfo>

  <section id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      This describes the 'poll' contribution. It provides functionality to quickly make a poll in
      MMBase. It supports IP-checking and cookie/session checking.
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="installation">
    <title>Installation</title>
    <para>
      Placing mmbase-poll.jar in WEB-INF/lib suffices to provide the needed builders, and tags to
      fully customize your own poll. The component blocks are implementations using JSP so those JSP
      can be installed too..
    </para>
    <para>
      Component blocks are only supported in MMBase versions beyond 1.8.  The rest of the
      functionality also works with MMBase 1.8. 
    </para>
    <para>
      An editwizard task definition is available in the directory 'tasks'.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="tags">
    <title>mm-pol tags</title>
    <para>
      Using 'tag-files' a few tags are defined by the poll contribution. They are available by the
      following URL: xmlns:mm-poll="http://www.mmbase.org/tags/mm/poll"
    </para>
    <section id="vote">
      <title>mm-poll:vote tag</title>
      <para>
        This tag explores the request, and handles a vote of a user. It has several attributes.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="poll">
      <title>mm-poll:poll tag</title>
      <para>
        This tag explores whether the client already voted, and then iterates over the possible
        answers. It has a 'canvote' attribute which is executed if the client can still vote, and
        the jsp:body is execute if it cannot vote for the poll.
      </para>
      <para>
        This tag has a required attribute 'poll' to indicate about which poll it handles.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="blocks">
    <title>Component blocks</title>
    <para>
      A complete poll implementation using the provided builders and tags is available as 'blocks'
      of the poll 'component'. The components generic admin pages of MMBase will give an overview of
      those block hence you have installed mmbase-poll.jar.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="builders">
    <title>Builders</title>
    <para>
      The poll component provides three builders.
    </para>
    <section id="poll">
      <title>Poll</title>
      <para>
        The questions of the polls can be stored in here. Possible answers are posrel related nodes
        of the type 'answer'. The total number of given answers (so the sum of all 'total_answers'
        fields of the related answers, can be obtained by the function 'total'.
      </para>
      <para>
        If the mmbase crontab module is active, then the field 'total' will be used to periodically
        store this total number of answers. This may be essential if e.g. you want to sort on this
        total.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="answer">
      <title>Answer</title>
      <para>
        Nodes of this type are posrel related to nodes of the type 'poll', to provide the possible
        options. There should be at least 2 anwers related to every poll.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="ip">
      <title>IP</title>
      <para>
        The ip builder can store the given answer for certain IP's. E.g. by using the
        mm-poll:checkip tag it can also be used more generally.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

</article>