<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"
[]>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Cloud Context Security</title>
    <date>2003-09-12</date>
    <edition>$Id: cloudcontextsecurity.xml,v 1.2 2003-11-17 12:46:31 michiel Exp $</edition>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Michiel</firstname>
        <surname>Meeuwissen</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>Publieke Omroep</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>
        This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI
        Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source
        Initiative.
      </para>
      <para>
        The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can
        be read at the MMBase site. See <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink>
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>
  <section id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      MMBase has a pluggable security system. This means the object level security can be
      implemented on several ways. This document describes the 'cloud context' implementation for
      MMBase security.      
    </para>
    <para>
      The default security implementation for several MMBase releases was the normal 'context'
      security. This security implementation defines users, groups and so-called 'security
      contexts'. See also the documentation for 'context security configuration'.
    </para>
    <para>
      Often it is desirable to have a more dynamic security implementation which is more readily
      configurable than by opening an XML file on the server in your text editor. It would be nice
      if the concepts and relations described in this XML file could be modeled using MMBase
      objects and relation. Then security could be administrated in the same way MMBase nodes can be
      edited.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="object model">
    <title>Object model</title>
    <para>
      Because of the nature of this security implementation, the object model of your MMBase
      installation must be enriched with several new object types and relations types. This section
      describes the object model needed for this security implemenation.
    </para>
    <para>
      <graphic fileref="Security.jpg"/>
    </para>
    <section id="contexts">
      <title>Contexts</title>
      <para>
        All security contexts are represented in the 'mmbase-contexts' node manager. A certain context
        can grant the several security operations ('create', 'read', 'write', 'delete', 'change
        context') to groups or directly to users. This goes by the role 'grant' between mmbase-context
        and mmbaseusers and mmbasegroups.
      </para>
      <para>
        To which other security contexts a context of a certain node may be changed is fixed by the
        'allowed' relation between contexts objects.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="groups">
      <title>Groups</title>
      <para>
        Security contexts can grant rights to groups, modeled by the 'mmbasegroups' node
        manager. Groups can contain other groups (with the 'contains' relations). Such 'contained'
        groups inherit all rights.
      </para>
      <para>
        Groups of course also can contain actual users. And users of course inherit their rights
        from the groups they are in.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="users">
      <title>Users</title>
      <para>
        Users are represented by 'mmbaseusers' objects. Users authorize themselves with
        username/password combinations which are fields of this node manager (the password is stored
        md5 encrypted in the database).
      </para>
      <para>
        Security contexts can also attribute rights directly to users.
      </para>
      <para>
        User objects can have several statuses. A user can be 'active', 'new' or 'blocked'.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="ranks">
      <title>Ranks</title>
      <para>
        Besides the default ranks of the security frame-work, more ranks can be defined. This can be
        used to block low ranked users to certain parts of your site.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="editors">
    <title>Security editors</title>
    <para>
      If you know the object model sufficiently well, security can now be administrated by using
      'generic' editors. Cloud context security is however shipped with specialized editors.
    </para>
    <para>
     <graphic fileref="editors.png"/>
      These editors work only in MMBase-1.7. They are implemented as 'pieces of
      html', which makes it possible to include the entire editors into other
      editors (I use this to integrate them in the editors for a certain site),
      and you can configure extra links for users (e.g. make a link to a 'people'
      editwizard to relate people objects to accounts). There is an index.jsp
      available to use them stand-alone. 
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="extraadmins">
    <title>'Extra' administration accounts</title>
    <para>
      Normally the cloud context security should be configured completely in itself. But it is
      e.g. possible to forget the admin password or so, and then you could not do certain things any
      more. You could fix it by temporary disabling security in security.xml and then reset the
      admin password.
    </para>
    <para>
      This would however temporary let anybody in your web site, and it would be very
      vulnarable, in that time. When you switch it on then again, then all user have to login again,
      which is also a (however small) disadvantage. Therefore we have provided an extra feature, which we
      could refer to as 'extra administrators', which works by use of a property file
      'admins.properties' in &lt;config dir&gt;/security/admins.properties. This property file contains name/password combinations of
      'extra' administrators. The file is dynamically loaded and checked (you can change it, place
      it, remove it), so you can add and remove such administrators on a running MMBase (without affecting 'normal' users).  So as long as you
      have access to the file system, you can in this way always administrate you site running Cloud
      Context Security, in a reasonably secure way.
    </para>
  </section>
</article>
