<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"
[]>
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Cloud Context Security</title>
    <date>2003-09-12</date>
    <edition>$Id: cloudcontextsecurity.xml,v 1.6 2008-12-15 15:22:50 michiel Exp $</edition>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Michiel</firstname>
        <surname>Meeuwissen</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>Publieke Omroep</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>
        This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI
        Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source
        Initiative.
      </para>
      <para>
        The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can
        be read at the MMBase site. See <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink>
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>
  <section id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      MMBase has a pluggable security system. This means the object level security can be
      implemented on several ways. This document describes the 'cloud context' implementation for
      MMBase security.
    </para>
    <para>
      The default security implementation for several MMBase releases was the normal 'context'
      security. This security implementation defines users, groups and so-called 'security
      contexts' in an XML. See also the documentation for 'context security configuration'.
    </para>
    <para>
      Often it is desirable to have a more dynamic security implementation which is more readily
      configurable than by opening an XML file on the server in your text editor. It would be nice
      if the concepts and relations described in this XML file could be modeled using MMBase
      objects and relation. Then security could be administrated in the same way MMBase nodes can be
      edited.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="object_model">
    <title>Object model</title>
    <para>
      Because of the nature of this security implementation, the object model of your MMBase
      installation must be enriched with several new object types and relations types. This section
      describes the object model needed for this security implementation.
      <figure>
        <title>The Cloud Context Security Object Model</title>
        <graphic fileref="Security.jpg"/>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <section id="contexts">
      <title>Contexts</title>
      <para>
        All security contexts are represented in the 'mmbase-contexts' node manager. A certain context
        can grant the several security operations ('create', 'read', 'write', 'delete', 'change
        context') to groups or directly to users. This goes by the role 'grant' between mmbase-context
        and mmbase-users and mmbase-groups.
      </para>
      <para>
        To which other security contexts a context of a certain node may be changed is fixed by the
        'allowed' relation between contexts objects (this feature it turned off on default).
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="groups">
      <title>Groups</title>
      <para>
        Security contexts can grant rights to groups, modeled by the 'mmbase-groups' node
        manager. Groups can contain other groups (with the 'contains' relations). Such 'contained'
        groups inherit all rights.
      </para>
      <para>
        Groups of course also can contain actual users. And users of course inherit their rights
        from the groups they are in.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="users">
      <title>Users</title>
      <para>
        Users are represented by 'mmbase-users' objects. Users authorize themselves with
        user name/password combinations which are fields of this node manager (the password is stored
        md5 encrypted in the database).
      </para>
      <para>
        Security contexts can also attribute rights directly to users.
      </para>
      <para>
        User objects can have several statuses. A user can be 'active', 'new' or 'blocked'.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="ranks">
      <title>Ranks</title>
      <para>
        Besides the default ranks of the security frame-work, more ranks can be defined. This can be
        used to block low ranked users to certain parts of your site.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="buildernaming">
      <title>Naming</title>
      <para>
        The builders are for legacy reasons called 'mmbase-users', 'mmbase-groups', 'mmbase-contexts',
        'mmbase-ranks'. But because these things are essentially related to
        security (rather then to 'mmbase' which is a bit of a non-statement in this context..) the
        gui names of these builders will start with 'security' rather then with
        'mmbase'. So in generic editors you will see them listed under 's' rather then under 'm'.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="editors">
    <title>Security editors</title>
    <para>
      If you know the object model sufficiently well, security can now be administrated by using
      'generic' editors. Cloud context security is however shipped with specialized editors.
    </para>
    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>The Cloud Context Security Editors embedded in another editor</title>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="editors.png"/>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <title>The group editor</title>
        <screenshot>
          <graphic fileref="groupeditor.png"/>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      These editors are implemented as 'pieces of
      html', which makes it possible to include the entire editors into other
      editors (I use this to integrate them in the editors for a certain site),
      and you can configure extra links for users (e.g. make a link to a 'people'
      editwizard to relate people objects to accounts). There is an index.jsp
      available to use them stand-alone.
    </para>
    <para>
      When defining a new 'context' object with the security editors, it might be convenient to
      allow read rights on it to most or all users. To facilitate this, this editors looks for a group with
      alias 'mayreadallgroup' when creating a context object, and if it exists the read operation is
      automaticly link to it immediately.
    </para>
    <para>
      Often you would want to associate a context with every 'group' of users, so on the creation of
      one of those, you get the option to create to other one in one go.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is suggested that these security editors are installed in /mmbase/security (as the
      `install' target of the cloud context security application would do).
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="extraadmins">
    <title>'Extra' administration accounts</title>
    <para>
      Normally the cloud context security should be configured completely in itself. But it is
      e.g. possible to forget the admin password or so, and then you could not do certain things any
      more. You could fix it by temporary disabling security in security.xml and then reset the
      admin password.
    </para>
    <para>
      This would however temporary let anybody in your web site, and it would be very
      vulnerable, in that time. When you switch it on then again, then all user have to login again,
      which is also a (however small) disadvantage. Therefore we have provided an extra feature, which we
      could refer to as 'extra administrators', which works by use of a property file
      'admins.properties' in &lt;config dir&gt;/security/admins.properties. This property file contains name/password combinations of
      'extra' administrators. The file is dynamically loaded and checked (you can change it, place
      it, remove it), so you can add and remove such administrators on a running MMBase (without affecting 'normal' users).  So as long as you
      have access to the file system, you can in this way always administrate you site running Cloud
      Context Security, in a reasonably secure way.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="otheroptions">
    <title>Other configuration</title>
    <para>
      Some other things can be configured in cloud context security. These setting are available as 'properties' in the builder xml of mmbase-contexts.
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>readall</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If you don't care for read protection, you can considerably simplify configuration
              by setting this property to 'true'. Every object may always be read by every
              user. This should also have a positive effect on the performance impact of
              security.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>allcontextspossible</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Setting this to false, would make it possible to implement a simple kind of work flow
              using security, because then you must explicitly indicate which context may be changed to
              which other contexts explicitly. Unpublished nodes can then be owned by a security
              context which does not allow reading by everybody. You can arrange then that the
              context can only be changed in one direction (to publish). The security editors do currently
              not support this (no way to link to next context)
            </para>
            <para>
              If this property is true (the default), then you may change any object (on which you
              have the 'change context' right, to any other context (which you can see).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>maxcontextsinquery</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              When checking read rights, in the query things like 'WHERE owner in (&lt;list of contexts&gt;)' can
              appear. This property is an indication for how much the query may (expressed in the number of times
              one contexts is added to the query) grow. If the query would have to be more complex this is not
              done, but the result would need checking. This means also that the result of a 'count'
              on a query might not be exactly right any more, because it might have counted some
              objects which you are not allowed to actually read.
            </para>
            <para>
              Warnings will be issued in the log when this number is too small (a postprocessing of
              query-results is needed), which you can solve in several ways. Firstly you can
              increase this property. You can also simply the used query (perhaps it has
              an extraordinary lot of steps), and lastly you could also make sure that there is for
              any user only a limited number of contexts which he can see or a limited number of
              contexts which he can not see (the query must contain for every step either contain a
              list of all 'invisible' contexts or all 'visible' contexts).
            </para>
            <para>
              This property defaults to 50.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
    <section id="otherbuilders">
      <title>Using different builders</title>
      <para>
        Cloud context security provides the builder mmbaseuser, mmbasegroups, and mmbasecontexts to
        store authentication and authorization information in. In some cases, e.g. when trying to
        deploy cloud context security on an environment which used to have a different security
        implementation, it may be desired to use other builders to store users and context in.
      </para>
      <section id="other_users">
        <title>Using another builder to store users in</title>
        <para>If you want to store the user in a different builder, then you have to do the
        following</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose your builder</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>You can define a 'security_editor_fields' property in this builder, to defined
            which fields must be edited in the the security editors.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Extend
            <classname>org.mmbase.security.implementation.cloudcontext.Authenticate</classname> and
            override the method getUserProvider. Implement your own <classname>Provider</classname>, it can e.g. be the
            class of your own users builder, and implement in your
            <classname>Authenticate</classname> how it should be obtained. The method
            <function>getUserBuilder</function> should return the builder (<constant>this</constant>
            in case the <classname>Provider</classname> <emphasis>is</emphasis> the builder).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Make sure the relations &lt;your builder&gt; to mmbaseranks with role 'rank',
            from mmbasegroups to &lt;your builder&gt; with role 'contains' and mmbasecontext to
            &lt;your builder &gt; with role 'grants' are possible.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section id="other_context">
        <title>Using another builder to store possible contexts</title>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="conversion">
    <title>Conversion from `XML' context security</title>
    <para>
      A conversion tool which read the XML file from the old style context security is
      available.
    </para>
    <para>
      This tool reads all users, groups and contexts from this file and matches them with
      the existing users, groups and contexts (by username, name and name). All non existing ones
      are created. After that also the `group structure' (which groups and users are contains by
      which groups) is copied (That might result in 'double' links, but that does not matter). And
      finally also the rights relations are created which are defined in the XML.
    </para>
    <para>
      The tool is available in the 'admin' directory of the security editors (there is no link, you
      need to make up the URL yourself, it might probably be /mmbase/security/admin, depending on
      where you put the editors).
    </para>
    <para>
      The inverse operation; writing back the security configuration to an XML which can be read by
      the `XML' context security implementation is not yet available (and it is a bit tricky because
      the passwords are plain text in the XML, but are md5 encrypted in the cloud).
    </para>
  </section>
</article>
