<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
<article class="specification">

  <articleinfo>
    <title>MMBase Lucene module</title>
    <date>2005-12-24</date>
    <edition>$Id: lucene.xml,v 1.2 2006-01-11 16:01:20 pierre Exp $</edition>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Pierre</firstname>
        <surname>van Rooden</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <firstname>Michiel</firstname>
        <surname>Meeuwissen</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <abstract>
      <para>Lucene</para>
    </abstract>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>
      <para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site. See <ulink url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink></para>
    </legalnotice>

  </articleinfo>

  <section id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      Lucene indexing is about full text search indexing. See <ulink url="http://lucene.apache.org/">the internet site of Lucene</ulink>. Most databases support this natively, but Lucene can do it too. Indices can be defined using java code (e.g. by JDBC connections or HTTP connections). MMBase is a database independent product, so database independent indexing like Lucene provides fits well in our scheme, and can easily be implemented using the MMBase bridge interfaces to provide the data to be indexed.
    </para>
    <para>
      This document is about a Lucene implementation as an MMBase 'module'. Basicly this provides a configuration file to configure queries to an MMBase repository, which are then used to produces Lucene indices. Furthermore, of course, it provides an MMBase way to access the search functionality itself (which is based on the MMBase 'function framework').
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="installation">
    <title>Installation</title>
    <para>
      Placing mmbase-lucene.jar in WEB-INF/lib suffices to provide the functionality and an activated MMBase module. You may also want to install mmbase-crontab.jar to schedule periodic full indices.
    </para>
    <para>
      You then also need to define indices, which can be done in a file &lt;config&gt;/utils/luceneindex.xml. For more information about that see the chapter about configuration in the present document.
    </para>
    <para>
      Some administration pages are provided too. We suggest installing those in /mmbase/lucene. You may want to trigger an initial full index, after defining those.
    </para>
    <para>
      Then of course you need to integrate a Lucene search in your site. A generic search tool is provided among the Lucene admin pages.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="configuration">
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para>
      The hardest part of the configuration of the Lucene index is of course the definition of the indices itself. The luceneindex.xml configuration file basicly looks like this:
      <example>
        <title>lucenindex.xml</title>
        <programlisting id="lucenindex.xmll"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<luceneindex
 xmlns="http://www.mmbase.org/xmlns/luceneindex"
 xmlns:mmsq="http://www.mmbase.org/xmlns/searchquery"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mmbase.org/xmlns/luceneindex http://www.mmbase.org/xmlns/luceneindex.xsd">
  <index >
    <analyzer class="org.mmbase.module.lucene.analysis.nl.StandardCleaningAnalyzer" />
    <!-- default index configuration -->
    ....
  </index>
  <index name="forum">
    <analyzer class="org.mmbase.module.lucene.analysis.nl.StandardCleaningAnalyzer" />
    <!-- yet another index -->
    ..
  </index>
</luceneindex>
]]>
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      So, you can have several indexes, each with its own 'analyzer' (a Lucene concept, see <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/lucene/..">API Doc for Analyzers</ulink>). Below each 'index' tag there can be 1 or more XML pieces defining a query to create the index. If more than one, then the definitions will be combined to one bigger index.
    </para>
    <para>
      A 'list' subtag defines an MMBase index, in a more or less MMBase taglib-like fashion.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>MMBase indices</title>
      <para>
        'list' subtags defined MMBase queries.
      <example>
        <title>lucenindex.xml</title>
        <programlisting id="lucenindex.xmll"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<luceneindex
 xmlns="http://www.mmbase.org/xmlns/luceneindex"
 xmlns:mmsq="http://www.mmbase.org/xmlns/searchquery"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mmbase.org/xmlns/luceneindex http://www.mmbase.org/xmlns/luceneindex.xsd">
  <index >
    <analyzer class="org.mmbase.module.lucene.analysis.nl.StandardCleaningAnalyzer" />
    <list type="products">
      <mmsq:constraint field="begin" operator="less"    value="today" />
      <mmsq:constraint field="end"   operator="greater" value="today" />
      <mmsq:field name="title" />
      <mmsq:field name="subtitle" />
      <mmsq:field name="intro" />
      <mmsq:field name="body" />
      <mmsq:field name="begin" />
      <mmsq:field name="end" />
    </list>

  </index>
  ... more indices
</luceneindex>
]]>
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Subindices</title>
      <para>
        It is also possible to add 'related' subtags to 'list'.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Other types of indices</title>
      <para>
        Since Lucene provides a much more generic functionality, the configuration file of this module keeps the option open that you want to do more then just indexing MMBase.
      </para>
      <para>
        Currently one alternative is provided: Direct JDBC access. Others can be imagined, like indexing of JSP sources (direct indexing of the resources of the web-app), or using http connection to the MMBase web-app (using HTTP connections), which would provide a google like full-index.
      </para>
      <section>
        <title>Direct access to JDBC</title>
        <para>
          Can be defined with the 'jdbc' subtag of 'index'. At the moment the implementation supposes that the jdbc connection should go to the same database as the MMBase instance. More general jdbc connection configuration may easily be added.
        </para>
        <para>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="history">
    <title>History</title>
    <para>
      There are currently two publicly available Lucene modules. The site http://mmapps.sourceforge.net provides an alternate version, careted by Finalist, which works on MMBase 1.7.</para>
    <para>
      The version you are looking at now was developed on the 1.8 version of MMBase.
    </para>
  </section>
</article>